Not in your backyard. Not yet.
Gasland is a documentary film directed by Josh Fox.
It is happening all across America-rural landowners wake up one day to find a
lucrative offer from an energy company wanting to lease their property.
The company hopes to tap into a reservoir dubbed the "Saudi Arabia of natural gas." Halliburton developed a way to get the gas out of the ground-a
hydraulic drilling process called "fracking"-and suddenly America finds itself on the precipice of becoming an energy superpower.
Self, played by Josh Fox.
Self (archive footage), played by Dick Cheney.
Self (archive footage), played by Pete Seeger.
Self (archive footage), played by Richard Nixon.
Self, played by Aubrey K. McClendon.
Self - Resident, played by Pat Fernelli.
Gasland is a 2010 American documentary film written and directed by Josh Fox.
It focuses on communities in the United States where natural gas drilling activity was a concern and, specifically, on
hydraulic fracturing ("fracking"), a method of stimulating production in otherwise impermeable rock.
The film was a key mobilizer for the anti-fracking movement, and "brought the term 'hydraulic
fracturing' into the nation's living rooms" according to The New York Times.
Fracking is a technique that has been used routinely since the late 1940s
as an aid to stimulating production in oil and gas wells.
Horizontal drilling, a recent innovation in drilling techniques, can create horizontal pathways deep within the
Earth, and has successfully incorporated hydraulic fracturing to release fluids from shale formations.
Horizontal drilling coupled with fracking has transformed the energy business, enabled vast new
supplies of natural gas, and advanced the goal of United States energy independence.
The film premiered at the 2010 Sundance Film Festival, where it
was awarded the Special Jury Prize for Documentary.
In June 2010, it premiered on HBO to an audience of 3 million homes, and it was seen
by over 250,000 audience members during a 250-city grassroots tour.
Among its numerous nominations and awards, the film was nominated for Best Documentary Feature at the 83rd Academy
Awards and won Outstanding Directing for Nonfiction Programming at the 63rd Primetime Emmy Awards.
The film explores themes of gas, pollution,
energy, polluted river, contamination.